Hello and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan and today we're going to
be learning about nuclear chemistry,
radiation, and its applications.
So what we're going to be diving
into is what is radioactive decay,
What do we mean by a nuclear
reaction versus a chemical reaction?
And we're going to be looking at
essentially the ionizing power and the
penetrating power of the different types
of radiation and some of the Applications
that this has to do in the world around
us and in the health science field.
Now when we're talking about
radiation This is not, this is
something that's not brand new.
It's been around for a very long time.
When it first started to come
around was right after the advent
of the periodic table right in those
1860s is when scientists started to
explore new possibilities of what
are the atoms truly made out of.
Now from that they started to realize
that well the atom is contains of
protons, neutrons, and electrons.
What are they exactly capable of?
Well, one of the first discoveries about
these was that there were X rays being
given off by different elements and
they weren't entirely sure exactly what
they were, um, until a Wilhelm Rottingen
discovered some of the basic properties
of X rays by essentially he took an X ray
of his wife's hand, um, back in 1890s.
And for something that is.
over 130 years old.
It actually has very good resolution.
You can see the bones.
You can see the rings on her hand.
Um, even if you zoom in, you can
even see her, her bracelet with our
keys on in this x ray is able to
resolve all those little details.
Now, once that was really seen,
what that showed is that with this
technology, the x rays, which is a form
of radiation, has a penetrating power.
Now, but for some reason, your
bones all of a sudden don't
allow those x rays to go through.
It goes through skin, but not bones.
Why?
What exactly does it often do?
Now, from there, in the 1890s,
several scientists, mainly with
Marie Curie, her husband Pierre
And another famous scientist named
Becquerel discovered all these
different properties behind radiation.
Now, originally Marie Curie was
first awarded the Nobel Prize in
1903 by the physics community for her
discovery with radiation splitting
with those other two scientists.
But she is one that, she's one of the
fir, one of the first people, her first
woman to, to have two nail blow prizes,
one for physics, one for chemistry, and
her one for chemistry was discovering
the the elements radium and polonium,
which were also radioactive species.
So with this, Sheik was the first one
to coin that term radioactive, meaning
that there are these species that seem
to give this signature or that something
that can be, that's being given off.
It's an invisible light source that
we cannot see with our own hands.
Do this unstable nature
of, of these nuclei.
And from there, people believed
that this was this new cool thing
that they could do all kinds of
really cool effects from it, right?
They, they glowed in the dark.
They did all these cool things until
they started to realize that there's
a lot of hazards behind radiation,
which we're going to be talking
about and looking into in this video.
So let's dive in and let's try to take
a look at a little bit more about this.
So the first thing is
what is radioactive decay?
So the first idea here is that whenever
you have a radioactive isotope.
That is an element with
an unstable nucleus.
Now when we say that's unstable, what
it's going to want to do is that they
spontaneously will decay, meaning
it will just, just happen, and it's
going to decay into smaller nuclei.
And when that happens, when it
breaks down, it's going to emit
radiation as one of, as essentially,
it's a way to release itself.
How can it try to, Bring
itself to a more stable state.
That's the goal of all even
chemical reactions and nuclear
reactions is stability, right?
That's even our goal as humans.
We want to be stable.
So, whenever this happens, a nuclide
that is, when I say a nuclide, this is
referring to a nucleus of a specific atom.
All nuclides, generally for these
that are radioactive, usually
it's 84 or more protons are always
considered to be radioactive.
So if you look at your periodic
table, anything that's 84 and
below, they are radioactive species.
They are very uncommon elements, but
they are the ones that tend to be that
what we see like uranium, polonium,
plutonium, radium, all these types
of elements are considered to be
very radioactive and very dangerous.
So why exactly do they decay?
Well, what is this all about?
Well, the whole idea here is that
nuclei that are unstable, it's kind
of, it's extremely difficult for
it to be able to maintain itself.
So when we have a very big, Nucleus that
has all these neutrons, all these protons.
One way to kind of think about it is
it's sort of like trying to juggle a
bunch of things in your arms, right?
If I have my hands full with like,
let's say a bunch of, let's say
fruit or apples or something, and I
have like four or five in my arms,
that's not too hold hard to cradle.
But if all of a sudden I have 50
to 60 apples and I don't have a
basket to hold them, they're gonna
start kind of tumbling out and
start being really hard to maintain.
Well, that's kind of what's happening.
It gets really hard for the nucleus
to hold the all of this together.
So one thing is that we actually can
currently see is that small nuclei
generally have a one-to-One ratio
between their neutrons and their
protons, and then larger nuclei start
to start to crouch towards this one and
a half neutrons for every one proton.
We're essentially we can actually
plot this and we can see this,
um, with, uh, what was what is
known as the band of stability.
So one thing is that we have this
one to one ratio, which is this red
line right down here down the middle.
So this is where it's one
neutron to one proton.
And all the way at the bottom, these
are like your beginning elements.
So things that you can kind of think of.
Like let's say if we have a helium
for example, right helium has
Has two neutrons to two protons.
So it's four to helium something
like lithium is six Three Li
carbon is twelve and six, right?
So it's all our six neutrons six
protons Three protons, three neutrons.
There's a one to one ratio
at the very beginning.
But then all of a sudden, that band
of stability starts to kind of venture
farther and farther away from that point.
Now, if things kind of wander outside
of this stable region of this, this
ratio that exists, That's when we start
getting these different decay patterns,
where they're going to fall apart.
So if something is a little bit
lower than this region, you'll see
that I'll do positron emission.
If it goes above, it's beta decay.
It all depends, does the
element kind of exist there.
Now this isn't something
you have to calculate.
But it's something that to be
aware of right if it goes a
little bit outside the norms.
It's considered to be Unstable, but
let's take a look at the different
reaction types So the first thing is
realizing what is the difference between
a chemical reaction and a nuclear one?
Well, the whole idea here is when
we've been learning all about chemistry
throughout all the different chapters
Chemical reactions all involve the
rearrangement of the electrons,
meaning that electrons are being
exchanged between species, right?
You see that their atoms are
gaining electrons or losing
electrons or sharing them.
It's all about how the different atoms
will be connecting to one another.
via this different, how these electrons
are being transferred or shared.
Now, the thing about it though, is
that there's no change to the nuclei of
these different species, meaning that we
never touched the number of protons, the
number of neutrons, that never changes.
The only thing that changed was electrons.
So the big thing there is that the
element identity remains the same.
Even if a reaction happens, let's say
if I have oxygen in a reaction and it
turns into a product, there's still
going to be oxygen atoms on the left.
There's still going to be
oxygen atoms on the right.
They're still going to have the same
atomic mass, same atomic number.
That is always the same.
It's never going to change.
Whereas if I have a nuclear reaction,
well, that's when there's actually
a change in the nuclei, in the
actual inner core of this atom.
It's going to be having, uh, the
protons could change, the neutrons
can change, something is changing
in the core of this species.
So because of that, there's a good
chance that the identity of the
element can change as a result.
So meaning maybe the number of neutrons
changes, if the protons change, it's
going to become something different.
We're all, and the thing is, we're
interested in what new nuclei form.
We don't really care about the charges
in nuclear chemistry, so we don't really
worry about the pluses and minuses.
We're adding up what is the masses.
in the number of protons.
So when we look at these different
nuclear equations, what they are is
we're essentially we're adding, we're
adding the top left and the right
and making sure everything matches.
So what you're always going to see
is some kind of parent nuclide And
it's going to be decaying into a
daughter nucleoid and breaking apart.
So when I said that the left and
the right should match, well, what
we're going to be checking is the
atomic number and the atomic mass.
So when we have our atomic mass, so on
the left here, so we have, remember these
were A and Z is how we would denote those.
So they have to match on both sides.
So if you see the mass is 238, that means
that the total of the mass on the right
hand side also has to be 238, right?
If you take 234 plus 4, it
also equals 238, so it matches.
Same thing with the atomic numbers, right?
If you look on the right hand side,
it's 90 plus 2, that's 92 total.
It matches the atomic number on the left.
So all these particles, they can't
just vanish on us, but it did
change the identity of the species.
It decayed, therefore it lost
protons, and you can see that, ooh,
because it's now a number of 90,
it's going to be something new.
Let's look at the different types
of radiation and try to make sure we
understand all the different types.
In my previous video, there were four
major types of nuclear equations,
and if you want to learn how to
balance nuclear equations, I would
recommend watching that video first.
So, when it comes to the four different
types, the first one is alpha decay.
So whenever we have alpha decay,
the whole idea here is that the
nuclei is losing two neutrons and
then two protons alongside of it.
So when it loses the two neutrons,
two protons, the way that we can
actually illustrate that is by it's
the same thing as a helium atom, right?
If you remember the mass of
helium, it has two protons, right?
Which we can see.
Um, from the two that's down below here.
And when you add those two protons
to the two neutrons, this is where
we will get a four for its atomic
number, sorry, for its atomic mass.
Now with that, when we are trying
to look at these reactions, you can
still see that everything equals up.
So when we do four plus
two 18 equals to 22.
And then 2 plus 86 is equal to 88.
Alpha decay is losing
2 neutrons, 2 protons.
So we can show that with a helium atom.
Now on to our next one.
Beta emission is when a neutron
is converted to a proton.
Meaning that when that happens, an
electron or beta particle is released.
So this is a very, very
high energy electron.
So when this happens, what you're
going to be seeing, so I have a
neutron on the left hand side written
as a dark blue, and it's converting
to a proton, which is shown in pink.
So when this happens, the one thing
you're going to notice is that the
mass number stays the same because
the way that we show a beta particle
is with a zero and a negative one.
So this would be a beta particle.
Um, and then typically we
write it as an electron.
Another way to show this as well
is writing zero and negative
one with a beta symbol as well.
And the one thing that with this
type of decay process, you'll see
that the atomic mass still equals to
14 on the, on the right hand side.
And then on the left, and
you also see that the total
of the atomic number is six.
So it matches the two, the two sides.
The mass number stays the same, the atomic
number increases, so this is a beta decay.
Now there's also the
opposite form of beta decay.
which is referring to instead of the
beta particle coming off as a product,
sometimes you can also have where an
electron can be absorbed by the nucleus.
So if that is to happen where an electron
is captured by the nucleus, because you
got to kind of think that electrons,
they are attracted to the nucleus.
They're always trying to
get in contact with it.
So what happens if it does happen?
If that occurs in an unstable
atom, a proton is, in that case,
going to be converted to a neutron.
So it's going to be the opposite
situation that's going to happen.
So what we'll see is we'll see that, that
electron or that beta particle is going
to be on the left hand side instead,
and you're still going to do the same
math where we're adding up 14 plus zero.
Um, which I meant to write this as an
11 over here, and then you'll still see
at the bottom is going to equal up to,
so six plus negative one, it's going
to be equal to five on the other side.
Right?
So those two parts will still match.
So it's just the two types.
So it's in case you come across
that vocabulary term of it
being captured, that's when the
electron falls into the nuclei.
Let's look into our next
two types of radiation.
So when we have positron emission, what
we are going to be seeing here is when
it's going to be when a proton sheds
its positive charge to become a neutron.
So it's very, very similar
to electron capture.
But instead, what you're going to be
seeing is that when that proton is
going to convert to a neutron, so I
have a proton drawn, shown in pink
here, it's converting to a neutron.
And what the way that we are going
to show that, that positron emission
is with a zero and a plus one.
And what you can see is if I add up
the masses, it's still going to be a
total of 11 on top So, And then the
bottom is going to be five plus one.
It's going to be a total of six
on the bottom, which is equal
to our products on the left.
So when you have a positron emission,
the mass number stays the same.
The atomic number decreases by one.
Okay.
So this is one thing to
kind of keep in mind too.
Now, other things to keep in the
thought process here is that your proton
and neutron counts are changing too.
So in this type of example, so
being that we had, if you look at
carbon, right, we had six protons.
Well, it's being converted
to a total of five protons.
So we have five protons and six neutrons.
And on the left you have six
protons and five neutrons.
So you can see that the proton and
neutron counts are changing too.
You can do this for any of them by
keeping track of how many protons and
neutrons are, which we'll be doing in
our next practice problem video as well.
Let's look at our last one.
The last one is gamma emission.
So what does gamma emission all
has to do with whenever you have
a very unstable nuclei, where it
needs to try to release energy.
So gamma rays, what they are,
it is a form of electromagnetic
radiation in the form of light.
So these are high energy photons
that are being released and they
are traveling at the speed of light.
So whenever this happens, this can be
used in very many practical applications
because they travel very fast and they
penetrate through almost everything.
Um, but as a result being that they
penetrate through a lot of things, they
don't ionize everything in their path.
So we'll talk about that too.
So it's all going to be shown with zeros
all around it, where it's just going to
be releasing that energy as a result.
Let's take a look at the next one.
So when it comes to penetrating
and ionizing ability, so
penetrating all has to do with
what the size of the particle is.
The heavier it is, the harder it is to
actually go through different things.
The lighter it is, the more
different surfaces it's going to
completely just plow right through.
So, what I have here is I have
a picture that has paper, skin,
metal, water, concrete, and lead.
So, there's all the different types of
different things that you could come in
contact with radiation really easily.
So, if you were to say what's
the heaviest particle, well, that
would be an alpha particle because
it had two neutrons, two protons.
So something like that, well, it can
only really, it would hit a piece
of paper and it would bounce off.
Okay.
Thank you.
The issue with that, though, is that
when it hits that paper, it's going to
ionize that surface very heavily because
this is a very, very dangerous particle.
Now on top of that, well, whenever
you have ionite, whenever you have the
penetrating ability, the lighter it gets,
the more surfaces it can go through.
So something like a beta particle
can travel through human skin.
but it would end up stopping via metal.
So if you had just had a metal surface
or maybe the side of a building,
it would easily stop to that.
Neutrons can are something that goes
through a lot of different surfaces,
which can be a little frightening, but
generally whenever it comes to a neutron
emitter, it's kept inside of water
or there's some kind of water shield.
because water will just absorb that,
that neutron to make deuterium.
So now when we have something
like gamma rays, gamma penetrates
almost everything except for lead.
So this is why a lot of different, um,
when it comes to patients, do an x rays
they will have like a lead line vest.
There's also usually whenever there's
a gamma ray emitting, gamma rays are
stronger in x rays, keep that in mind.
So whenever there is a gamma ray it's
usually kept in a lead container so that
way it protects everybody around it.
So now when it comes to
penetrating ability, the
ionization ability is the opposite.
So if something travels a lot
farther it's going to actually have.
a lower ionization ability.
And that's because of how
fast these particles move.
So gamma rays move at the speed of light.
So that's why they can go through
so many different things so quickly.
Now, being that they are going through
so fast, they're not going to ionize
as many different species in its path.
So if you come across gamma rays,
It won't ionize like your DNA,
your skin, everything that it
comes in contact with as easily.
It's something that you could
essentially use for a longer period
of time to maybe get rid of a cancer
tumor or as a potential therapy.
Now, alpha particles, on the other hand,
being that when they can't penetrate
anything, They are so heavy, they will
come in contact with things for a lot
longer, they'll have a longer dosage time.
So as a result, they will end
up ionizing everything they
are coming in contact with.
So if you end up ingesting an
alpha particle by accident, so
let's say if you're not careful
with cleaning up after yourself.
It can't come out of your skin, so
it's something that will stay inside
you for a very long period of time.
So it's a little scary.
Beta particles are usually right in
the middle, so it's something that can
be used to, to maybe damage something,
but it also, or maybe even used as
a contrasting agent because it can
leave your body, but it still has
some harmful effects behind it too.
So let's look at an example when it comes
to occupational safety when it comes to
the penetrating and ionizing ability.
Okay.
So one of the different stories of
when it comes to radiation is that
many different people have died due to
exposure of radiation because the effects
were not understood until probably
until the 1930s and 1940s of what
radiation was truly capable of doing.
We knew that it was powerful, that
it had a lot of applications, and
it was this really exciting thing at
the time period, but people did not
entirely understand it completely.
So, when radiation was first started
to determine that it was dangerous was
around the early 1910s, um, where people
started, because they were essentially
putting it in everything at the time.
When Marie Curie and all those other
scientists discovered it, they were
putting it into makeup, putting it
into, uh, plates, cups, beauty products,
you name it, because it had that glow
in the dark quality to it, so a lot
of people wanted to put it in things.
Now, as a result, people were getting
sick, it had a lot of problems, especially
in Europe where this really took off.
Now, in the U.
S., there wasn't really a lot of
radioactive products available, except
for there's one major, major case,
which is known, which is, a lot of
it is, uh, called the radium girls.
So if you ever kind of there's
actually a movie about it now, um, if
something's even interesting to read
about, it's actually a pretty sad
story is that the factories during that
time period hired a lot of women to
paint watch faces with radium paint.
Now why would they use radium paint?
Well, it was something that would be this
glow in the dark watch where airplane
pilots could easily see the hands on it.
because it'd be glowing.
Now the thing about this glow in
dark paint is that being as made of
radium that is a radioactive chemical
which can you can get very sick from.
And this decay process that it
undergoes is alpha decay, meaning
that what the girls were doing is that
they were told in order to get a very
nice straight line on the thing to
lick the edge of their paintbrush and
then to dip in the chemicals to paint
it and then keep licking the edge.
So what was happening is they were getting
it in their mouth and it'd be ingested
and it would lead to that exposure.
So being that we're talking about
alpha decay, as I was mentioning, is.
It can't go through paper.
So if you eat it, it can't
really leave out of you.
It's going to do a ton of damage.
So, as a result, a lot of these girls
ended up getting bone cancer, where
their jaws would fall off, they would
get anemia, they would get necrosis,
meaning that their body is falling apart.
If you really want to get into
it, you can Google that and see
some of the images behind that.
It can be a little vivid as a warning,
um, but it's something that really
shows what this is capable of.
So, if you're someone who wants to work
in radiation technology, you've got to
treat it very seriously because it can be
something that can be very, very damaging.
As a huge application, but it's
very dangerous at the same time.
So let's look at how we can detect it so
we can protect ourselves from radiation.
So there are a couple different ways to
detect radiation to make sure that we
are safe from it when we are handling it.
The most common way is whenever
you use a Geiger counter.
So what exactly is a Geiger counter?
It's essentially that device that
you've seen on different TV shows
and it does that little tick, tick,
tick, tick, tick, tick sound whenever
it's near a radiation source.
Well what it's essentially doing
is that when you have radioactive
rays, it causes the air to ionize.
And what the Geiger counter is going to
actually do, it's going to count all the
different electrons that are being, that
are being released from this ionization.
So when the electrons are generated,
uh, essentially we'll be having argon
gas is going to be ionized by the
radioactive rays and we'll detect that,
um, from the radioactive material.
So this is something that when they have
any type of radiation leak or any type of.
If there's like a nuclear device or
anything that could be really problematic,
you'll see a Geiger counterskip
that get brought out to make sure
people are not being exposed to it.
So that's one way.
Um, another way is generally for anyone
that works in radiation technology, if
they're an x ray technician or someone
that actually might help with a lot
of different radiation therapy and
they are working around a lot of this.
Um, there's another way where if you
have radioactive rays, they can expose
a light protected photographic film.
So when that happens, it's something
that is like a little badge that
generally these workers will wear on
their chest, and it will change colors
if you are around too much radiation.
So it's like an Early warning
system rather than because you
don't know you can't see it, right?
So this is something that will change
colors when when you're near too
much radiation So a lot of people
wear it around like sensitive areas.
That could be more Susceptible to
radiation whether it's like genitalia
or if you are someone who's pregnant For
example then wearing it around like a
baby to eventually be is a really good
spot to put it to make sure hey Everything
is going to be okay Um, sometimes
you're also around radioactive sources.
You might have many Geiger counters near
them in case there's a radiation leak.
So it's something just that if you
have a small exposure, it's normal,
but you don't want a prolonged chronic
long term exposure is really the idea.
And the whole reason for this
is, well, when I, when talk about
radiation, we think like, Oh,
it's all these unstable things.
It's only found in like the lab
somewhere in like the middle of nowhere.
No, a lot of this is natural
radiate, radioactive species.
It is all around you right now.
You are exposed to radiation
at all times, right?
It's not always as alpha, beta,
gamma, gamma decay, all this stuff.
There are, radiation is light, right?
So you are exposed to
light source all the time.
They're not as strong as these other
sources, but radiation's everywhere.
So there are isotopes that
are radioactive, right?
So right now, like, you have
radioactive particles inside of you.
So, If you have like carbon 14, because
you are made of mainly out of carbon,
some of that carbon is carbon 14, which
is radioactive, and it's always emitting,
uh, different radioactive particles.
Um, a lot of soil samples that we have
are, there's something that you can, that
you can detect radioactive particles.
It's more or less in different
areas, but that's possible.
Food also, any type of food product,
whether it's carbon, or if you have like
bananas, for example, they have potassium
40, which is a radioactive chemical.
People being near anybody
actually is radioactive.
So if you're wondering what's that
attraction between people, it's
actually secretly the radiation
between different people, um, or
just being in the open, right?
So if you think a UV light coming from
the sun, that is a form of radiation,
but if it wasn't for your ozone layer,
we'd kind of all be dead due to the
cosmic rays from the interstellar space.
So there is essentially the
ozone layers always protecting
us because it absorbs most of the
gamma rays that exist in space.
This is also one of the reasons why
astronauts need to wear spacesuits.
It's not just for the lack of
oxygen and, um, how cold it is.
It's also to protect them from cosmic
radiation, which would even be worse.
Um, one of the things about this is even
though the ozone layer actually does
this, if you fly a lot, You actually
are going to be more susceptible
to higher doses of radiation.
Generally, pilots and flight attendants
that are flying every single day, they
will actually, it's confirmed that they
always have a higher doses of radiation.
They're usually checked more often to make
sure, hey, your levels are within, within
a safe region, within your occupation.
So now what are the different
types of applications behind this?
Well, with this there are all kinds of
applications, but so some of them, one
of the big ones is carbon dating, or
for fossils, artifacts, different rocks.
You can use, you can, the carbon
14 exists in all different
species, living and non living.
And depending on how much of it there
is, we can do calculations to figure
out, well, what was the original half
lifes of things, so you can figure
out how much there should be in a
given sample of when it was created.
So carbon dating is
really, really prevalent.
Another one is when it comes to alternate
fuel sources, being that where you
are trying to get away from fast, the
fossil fuel industry, one of the most,
the biggest ones is nuclear fission
in the terms of a power plant, right?
So if we split the atom, can it be used
because it generates so much energy?
Can it be used to try to power our cities
and to try to keep all the lights on?
Um, another example of nuclear fusion.
So fission is splitting fusion
is all about combining together.
So when we have that, that's how the
sun essentially shows all of its light.
And as a result, you have the
different types of radiation that's
being given off from it at all times.
The atomic bomb, which had been, if
you've seen the movie Oppenheimer
recently is a form of nuclear fission.
Um, in terms of radiation as
well, it's used to destroy human
tissue, whether in a medical
application, let's say if we want to.
Get rid of a tumor, for example,
or to get rid of a lesion, then
it can destroy human tissue.
Um, but the thing is though, it
has two sides of that coin, right?
You can use it for a good thing,
but it also, you can get radiation
poisoning, which is generally
whenever someone has radiation
treatment, they can get very sick.
They can get very weak because
radiation is flooding your body.
It's very bad for you.
Um, for a very prolonged period
of time, it can be very deadly.
This is actually how Marie Curie
did die from radiation poisoning.
Um, she only was, I think, probably
around, I think, less than 50 years old
by the time she passed away in the 1930s.
So radiation poisoning
slowly took her life.
Um, but the biggest application
is really a lot of the
imaging and medical treatment.
So depending on where you end up using
this, there's all kinds of different
applications for where this has been used
in our history over the past 120 years
because it's one of the biggest ones.
But being that many of you are
interested in medical, the medical
industry, I thought let's focus on
that and talk about some little cool
examples of really where this is used.
Um, where we use radiation treatments to
try to help and better, better people.
Okay.
So let's take a look.
So when it comes to medical scanning and
treatment that I picked two examples,
which are a little bit bigger to see.
So the first one is whenever
you have something known as
gamma knife radiosurgery.
So what this is, is actually takes
gamma rays and focuses it in a very,
very precise beam where it's like
using a scalpel to remove a tumor.
Okay.
Now, instead of it being a
traditional knife, it's going to
be using radiation to do this.
So what is actually happens here is when
we're using imaging technology, we can
shoot a gamma ray straight at the tumor.
And this will, by irradiating
and destroying this tumor,
it will stop all cell growth.
Now, keep in mind, this stops good
growth of good cells and of bad cells,
so that's where kind of the, the, uh,
you know, the coin flip is, but it
will destroy and try to stop any future
cancer growth within that region.
Now, the good news about this is something
that's doable without needing to actually
open a patient on the operating table.
So it removes a lot of the.
Um, general problems that can arise,
but in a will slowly destroy the cell.
So something that can be done over
multiple treatments over a long
period of time by focusing and
removing exactly where the tumors are.
And it has a and so far it seems to
be based on studies it has about the
same success as a regular surgery,
which is actually very promising.
Now another one which is probably one
of the most, one of the most common that
many of you will actually, if you do
go into nursing or radiation technology
that you're going to be sending patients
to, is whenever you have a CAT scan.
So whenever you, if you hit your head
real hard, you usually got to get your
CAT scan or an MRI to see like, hey,
is there any actual internal bleeding?
Is there a concussion?
Are there any problems?
So, the whole idea of what a CAT scan is,
is essentially you have an x ray machine
that is going to be rotating around your
body and it's going to make, creating a
3D image of the area that's being scanned.
Now, how does this all work?
Well, it's x rays that are going
through, which form a radiation.
Um, so essentially different
parts of the body will absorb it.
Bones absorb x rays, so you can
generally get bones x rays really well.
But usually we end up using a
chemical contrasting agent that
will absorb that radiation.
So that way it lights up on the scan.
So for example, let's say if you want to
see a brain scan, well, you can, you can
take 3D images of all the different layers
to really be able to see, well, where,
where exactly could there be a problem
at, or maybe if everything's all healthy.
Um, this is one of the reasons why in
anatomy you have to learn about all the
different planes of the body and how you
can try to view it so that way you are
able to interpret different data like this
and know exactly what it is that needs
to be referred to when we are trying to
understand how we are looking at the body.
Now other areas where contrast agents are
always required, this is usually where
it's more soft tissue, so muscles, organs.
Anywhere that you can easily,
uh, inject a contrasting agent or
even ingest a contrasting agent.
Um, maybe it might line something.
So here we have like the intestinal
track where it's really easy to, um,
try to, if you like engulf, uh, like
a barium, barium compound, that's kind
of like drinking chalk, essentially
it will align your entire test.
And so you can actually, so
the doctors can get an idea
like, Hey, is there a lead?
Is there maybe your intestines
have a hole in them?
Maybe is there something problem where
things are getting stuck somewhere?
Can they get a better idea
of, of what's inside of you?
with rather than doing an endoscopy.
So it's just another method for, for
looking at the body and getting a better
idea of what's going on inside you.
All right.
So this has been the kind of the
background information or radiation.
Um, just cause I thought it'd be
good to have a video on all this for
anyone that's interested, uh, just
the better try to educate all of
you into the whole entire promise.
Okay.
Well, thank you so much
for, for listening.
And I hope that this video, I hope you
learned something new from this video.
Um, and if you have any questions,
please feel free to ask.
You can always message me, um, or comment
below in the comments, message me, email
me, whatever it is that you need for help.
Okay?
And if this is your first time
here, if you haven't yet before,
hit that like and subscribe button
and thank you so much for watching.
I really appreciate you and I look
forward to seeing you next time.
Bye now.